Guide to the Oral Histories Documenting Yale University Women
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Polan, Mary Lake, 2007 November 28; Accession 2012-A-050
  From 1981-1985 Polan was an Assistant Professor in the Yale Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, then Associate Professor 1985-1990. In 1986 she was a visiting professor at Hunan Medical College, China. Polan left Yale in 1990 to become the Katharine Dexter McCormick and Stanley McCormick Memorial Professor at the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Stanford University School of Medicine, where she was also Chair from 1990 to 2005. Polan retired in 2005 but continued to practice, including a visiting professorship in the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, at Columbia University School of Medicine.
  Professor Polan served on the boards of numerous medical boards and corporations including Wyeth, DuPont and Proctor & Gamble. She was a founding member of the Board of Directors of the Society for the Advancement of Women's Health Research; served on the Board of Directors, New York Academy of Medicine; and as a Trustee of Connecticut College. She held many positions at the Institute of Medicine and the National Institutes of Health, and in such professional societies as the American College of Obstetrics and Gynecology and the American Society for Reproductive Medicine. She authored Second Seed (Charles Scribner, 1987), wrote and co-wrote 150 scientific articles, and contributed to or edited numerous books.
  Mary Lake Polan discusses her upbringing and education. She reflects on the ways in which her parents encouraged her to be independent and self-reliant, and how the all-girl Emma Willard School cultivated intellectual self-confidence, qualities which Polan believes enabled her to flourish in a scientific and medical environment. She talks at some length about her application to the Yale Biochemistry Graduate program and the experience of being a graduate student at Yale. She recalls her time living in the graduate women's college, Helen Hadley Hall, and in particular her experience as a resident fellow at Timothy Dwight College. She describes how women were excluded from Mory's and the Elizabethan Club. Particular tribute is paid to Dr. Joseph G. Gall, a pioneer in the field of cell biology, as an advisor and mentor. She recalls what it was like to be one of "Gall's Gals," the soubriquet given to the women graduate students and postdoctoral fellows who worked in Gall's laboratory. It was one of the few places at Yale in the late 1960s and early 1970s where women far outnumbered men. These women, whom Mary Polan acknowledges at some length, included Joan Steitz, Mary Clutter, Susan Gerbi, Virginia Walbot and Mary Lou Pardue, all of whom went on to have distinguished careers. Polan discusses how the postwar expansion of scientific education and the development of new areas of research in the United States benefited women. She recalls the establishment of Women in Cell Biology in 1971, believed to be the first such women's group in the American scientific community. Nevertheless she recalls that, despite growing opportunities for women in science, including new openings at Yale and other universities, many well qualified women remained at instructor or lecturer level.
  Polan contrasts her experiences as a science graduate with those as a medical student, and discusses what she perceives to be the very significant differences between science and medical education and culture, and why medicine was particularly difficult for women to negotiate. She talks at length about being the only female resident in the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology in the Yale School of Medicine and speculates on the extent to which difficulties for women in medicine were a result of gender or due to the hierarchical nature of medical training. She recalls her experience on the faculty at Yale Medical School, including relationships with colleagues, mentoring, salary inequities, and the challenge of managing a career, marriage and children. She explains why she left Yale and how her Yale experiences influenced her managerial style and vision as Chair of Stanford's Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology. She concludes by considering how medical culture has changed as a result of the increasing numbers of women entering the profession.
  - Audiorecording, 5; ; 3 hours and 16 minutes
    - Use copy, 1
  - Edited transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1)
- Quilligan, Maureen, 2007 April 10; Accession 2012-A-051
  Maureen Quilligan was born August 16, 1944, in Ann Arbor, Michigan, and brought up in Los Angeles where her father was a pediatrician. She took her B.A. and M.A. at the University of California, Berkeley (1965 and 1967 respectively). She earned her Ph.D. from Harvard University in 1973. She was Assistant Professor of English at Yale University from 1973 to 1978, then Associate Professor from 1978 to 1983, after which she taught at the University of Pennsylvania, where she was Acting Director of Women's Studies 1986-1987. In 2000 she was appointed the R. Florence Brinkley Professor of English and Professor of Women's Studies Program at Duke University. She was Chair of English there from 2000-2005.
  She is the author of four books: The Language of Allegory (Cornell U.P., 1979), Milton's Spenser: the Politics of Reading (Cornell U.P., 1983), The Allegory of Female Authority: Christine de Pizan's Cité des Dames (Cornell U.P., 1991), and Incest and Agency in Elizabeth's England (University of Pennsylvania P., 2005). In addition to publishing many articles on Renaissance writing and culture, she has co-edited several volumes of essays including Rewriting the Renaissance: the Discourses of Sexual Difference in Early Modern Europe (University of Chicago Press, 1986), Subject and Object in Renaissance Culture (Cambridge U.P., 1996) and Rereading the Black Legend: the Discourses of Religious and Racial Difference in the Renaissance Empires (University of Chicago Press, 2007).
  She has won several teaching awards including the Sidonie Clauss Prize for Teaching in the Humanities at Yale (1983).
  Maureen Quilligan briefly discusses her upbringing but talks at length about her intellectually and politically formative student years at U.C. Berkeley during the 1960s. She discusses the reasons she chose Harvard for her doctoral studies, her involvement in Harvard's Graduate Women's Organization, and pays tribute to the medievalist Morton Bloomfield, her supervisor, for his mentorship and sensitivities to gender issues. She details the circumstances surrounding her appointment at Yale, the excitement and challenges of her first job, and how she first began to focus on gender in her teaching and scholarship. Gender relations within the Yale Department of English are discussed extensively, particularly how they reflected departmental and institutional culture. She talks about the junior/senior faculty divide at Yale, the university's tenure process and how she responded to the competitive pressures of its intellectual community. An account is given of the first conference held at Yale in 1982 on gender in the Renaissance, organized by Nancy Vickers, Maureen Quilligan and her Yale colleague, Margaret Ferguson, and its impact on Renaissance studies at Yale and beyond. She recalls women in the English Department, including Marie Borroff, who was its first tenured woman and Patricia Spacks who was the first female Chair of the department, and reflects at length on the difficulties, including her own, of being a woman in academia. Quilligan also talks about the challenges of teaching at Yale in the 1970s, especially the challenge of shaping and implementing protocols in the newly coeducational environment. She speaks of her involvement at Yale in the campaign for affirmative action and the establishment of Women's Studies and, more generally, working at an institutional level to introduce gender into the curriculum and its importance as a catalyst to institutional change. She also comments on specific documents in the Yale University Archives to which she contributed during her time at Yale. The interview concludes with her thoughts on the current position of women in the academy, particularly in the context of the so-called "culture wars," and the role of the humanities in the public sphere.
  - Audiorecording, 1; ; 2 hours
    - Use copy, 1
  - Edited transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1)
- Skinner, H. Catherine W., 2007 June 12; Accession 2012-A-053
  H. Catherine W. Skinner was born in Brooklyn, New York, on January 25, 1931. She took her B.A. at Mount Holyoke College in 1952, followed by an M.A. from Radcliffe College in 1954. She met and married her husband, Brian Skinner, when they were both graduate students and thereafter her career followed his. While he was completing his Harvard Ph.D., she worked as a crystallographer at Harvard Medical School, 1954-1955. The Skinners moved to Australia when he was appointed to a position at the University of Adelaide. She gained her Ph.D. in mineralogy there in 1959. Brian Skinner's appointment at the United States Geological Survey in 1958 prompted their return to this country. With three small children, Catherine Skinner worked as a mineralogist at the National Institute of Arthritis and Metabolic Diseases, at the National Institutes of Health, 1961-1964, and then at the National Institute of Dental Research 1965-1966. In 1966, Brian Skinner's appointment as Professor of Geology brought them to Yale University. Catherine Skinner has held a number of faculty positions at Yale, including Research Associate, Department of Surgery, 1967-1972; Senior Research Associate, Department of Surgery, 1972-1975; and Associate Professor of Biochemistry in Surgery, 1978-1984; as well as a variety of lectureships and affiliated positions since 1967 in the departments of Biology, Geology, Orthopedic Surgery and the Peabody Museum. She was made a Senior Research Scientist in Geology in 2006 at the age of 75.
  During 1977-1983, Catherine Skinner was the first woman Master of Jonathan Edwards College and during 1985-1994, served as the first female President of the Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences. She has held a number of visiting professorships at the universities of Harvard, Cornell, Wyoming, Adelaide and Stanford. She was made a Fellow of the Geological Society of America (1989) and of the American Association for the Advancement of Science (1993). In addition she has chaired national committees at the National Academy of Science, the Geological Society of America and the National Research Council, as well as chairing or serving on many committees at Yale University and Yale-New Haven Hospital. She has written over 70 scientific papers on geology and health, and written or edited four books including Asbestos and other Fibrous Materials (Oxford University Press, 1988), Dana's New Mineralogy (John Wiley, 1997), Geology and Health: Closing the Gap (Oxford U.P., 2003), and most recently a chapter in The Earth, Source of Health and Hazard: an Introduction to Medical Geology (Annual Review of Earth and Planetary Sciences, 2007).
  Catherine Skinner talks about her family background and influences and the social expectations of young women in postwar America. She reflects extensively on her social and intellectual experiences at Mount Holyoke and Radcliffe colleges, and more generally on the importance of women's colleges as empowering intellectual communities for women of her generation. She recalls how and why newer scientific fields like molecular biology and environmental science have provided opportunities for women determined to pursue scientific careers in ways that the more traditional disciplines, like her own chosen field of geology, did not. Throughout the interview she talks about scientists, mostly male, who helped her carve out a career in academic science, and the personal qualities and social support systems she believes helped her to succeed. She reflects on the challenges she encountered in balancing marriage and family with a career, and how she negotiated the experience of often being the only woman in a man's world (as she describes it). She describes in detail how she found, and retained, employment as a scientist at Yale University, at a time when spousal hire was not an option, and addresses issues of status and salary in respect to women in the scientific community. A major part of the interview is devoted to Dr. Skinner's life as a College Master. She speculates on why she was offered the job, and the challenges it brought, especially during the 1977 Yale strike, and the effect it had on her family life. She also talks about the early years of co-education at Yale and how it and affirmative action changed the social and intellectual life of the university.
  - Audiorecording, 193; ; 3 hours and 15 minutes
    - Use copy, 1
  - Edited transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1)
- Spacks, Patricia Meyer, 2007 November 30; Accession 2012-A-054
  Patricia Meyer Spacks was born November 17, 1929, in San Francisco, California, and grew up mostly in Florida. She went to college at the age of fifteen graduating summa cum laude from Rollins College in 1949. After obtaining a Masters in 1950 from Yale, she went to the University of California at Berkeley where she earned her Ph.D. in English Literature in 1955. From 1954-1956 Spacks was an instructor at Indiana University, where she met her husband. She followed him first to Cambridge, England, and then to the University of Florida, where she found work as an instructor in English, 1958-1959. Her daughter was born there. During this time, with the encouragement of Aubrey L. Williams, she wrote her first book, The Varied God. Patricia Spacks moved with her family to Wellesley College in 1959 when she was hired first as an instructor, then as Assistant and Associate Professor. Awarded tenure early, she remained at Wellesley until 1979, serving as Chair of the English Department from 1968-1971. Recruited to Yale in 1979, Spacks served as the first female Chair in English from 1981-1985. She was appointed Neil Gray Jr. Professor of English in 1989. She left Yale in 1989, to become the Edgar F. Shannon Professor of English at the University of Virginia, where she served as Chair from 1991-1997. Patricia Spacks retired in 2005.
  Patricia Spacks has been the recipient of many honors and distinctions for her research and for services to her subject, including the Outstanding Faculty of Virginia Award, 1995; the Francis Andrew March Award, 1996; and an honorary Phi Beta Kappa, 1998. In 2000 she was elected the first Scholar in Residence in the Humanities at the American Academy of Arts and Sciences. She has been president of the Modern Languages Association, 1994, and of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 2001-2006. In addition Spacks has served on, amongst others, the boards of the American Council of Learned Societies and the National Humanities Center.
  Patricia Spacks is the author of many books and articles, including The Varied God (University of California Press, 1959); The Female Imagination (Knopf, 1975); The Adolescent Idea: Myths of Youth and the Adult Imagination (Basic Books, 1981); Gossip (Knopf, 1985); Boredom: The Literary History of a State of Mind (University of Chicago Press, 1995); Privacy: Concealing the Eighteenth-Century Self (University of Chicago Press, 2003); and Novel Beginnings: Experiments in Eighteenth-Century English Fiction (Yale University Press, 2006).
  Patricia Spacks talks about her background and upbringing, in particular her relationship with her father set within the context of expectations for young women of the period. She gives a lively account of the different intellectual, social and emotional challenges of her student years at Rollins College, Yale University, and the University of California at Berkeley. She recalls those teachers, like Bertrand Bronson at Berkeley, who encouraged her intellectual development. Throughout the interview Spacks describes the pleasures and challenges of teaching in both mixed and single-sex environments. She recounts her experiences as a young mother when she was teaching at the University of Florida and Wellesley College. Spacks details her awakening to feminism and in particular how she came to write The Female Imagination. Her experience of Yale culture, especially in the context of being the first female Chair of the Department of English, is described at length, along with the ways in which she believes her gender influenced both how she was expected to do the job and how she actually did it. The challenges of chairing the English Department, the difficulties of the tenure system for both male and female junior faculty, and the best means of nurturing women (particularly women graduate students) at that time are all addressed. Spacks explains why she left Yale and what she brought from her Yale experience to her work at the University of Virginia. In the last part of the interview she reflects on her work as president of the Modern Languages Association and the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the challenges of being a public intellectual and defender of the humanities in contemporary America, and the future of the academic profession and the position of women within it.
  - Audiorecording, 2; ; 2 hours and 25 minutes
    - Use copy, 1
  - Edited transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1)
- Trachtenberg, Betty Glassman, 2009 February 16; Accession 2012-A-055
  Permission to access must be obtained from interviewee until January 1, 2039.
  Betty Glassman Trachtenberg was born in 1933 and brought up in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. Her parents were Russian Jewish immigrants. In 1952, aged 19, she married Alan Trachtenberg, whose family lived in the same neighborhood. A talented pianist, she earned a Bachelor of Music from Ornstein School of Music in Philadelphia. In 1955 she had her first child, during the period when her husband was studying for a master's degree at the University of Connecticut, Storrs. Two more children followed in quick succession. From Storrs the family moved to Minneapolis for Alan Trachtenberg's Ph.D. During this time Trachtenberg taught music and was active in the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom. Alan Trachtenberg got his first faculty position at Pennsylvania State University at State College, PA; during their time there Betty Trachtenberg and a neighbor established a music academy. Following a year at Stanford University the Trachtenbergs came to Yale in 1969, when Alan Trachtenberg was appointed to a position in English and American Studies. For an initial period of three years she worked in New Haven teaching music to emotionally disturbed children, but after a year's sabbatical in London, UK, where she took a course at the Anna Freud Institute, Trachtenberg decided on a change of direction.
  Trachtenberg began her career at Yale in 1974 in the Summer Term Office. She then became assistant director in the Undergraduate Admissions Office, where she was the first director of admissions for the Eli Whitney Students Program, which oversees students of non-traditional age and background. Later she spent three years as associate director of Yale Summer Programs, before joining the Yale College Dean's Office (in 1984) as director of freshman affairs. In this position she was responsible for the freshman counselor and orientation programs. Trachtenberg retained this program portfolio when she became Dean of Student Affairs in 1987, the first woman to hold the position and one which she held for twenty years until her retirement in 2007. As Dean of Student Affairs she had a wide range of responsibilities, which included setting policies in student health and social conduct, participating in disciplinary, mediation and grievance procedures (including sexual harassment), encouraging student participation in university governance, overseeing student organizations, and advocating on behalf of Yale Women's Center. One of her many achievements as Dean was the founding of the ethnic counseling program. She was popularly known to Yale's undergraduates as the Dean of Sex, Drugs, and Rock-and-Roll.
  Betty Trachtenberg describes growing up in an extended Jewish family in Philadelphia, recalling the culture of a largely immigrant community and her own involvement in leftist politics during her teenage years. She speaks at length about being a young wife and mother in the 1950s, and being one of a group of young married women who were determined to maintain their own interests alongside having children and supporting their husbands through graduate school. She considers the extent to which she absorbed contemporary cultural assumptions about women's role in society. Her first impressions of Yale are described, together with the social challenges of being a young faculty wife and encounters with the wives of senior faculty. An account is given of how she got her first job in the Yale administration, the kinds of students who were admitted to the Eli Whitney Students Program in its early days, and the problems they faced (particularly the women). Trachtenberg then explains her reasons for standing down as director of summer programs and how her move to the Yale College Dean's Office came about. The challenges of the job of Director of Freshman Affairs, and the changes she made during her tenure, are outlined. She talks about her relationships with Judith Brandenburg, an associate dean of Yale College, and Patricia (Prish) Pierce. The bulk of the interview deals with Trachtenberg's twenty years as Dean of Student Affairs. Amongst the topics she discusses are her work with the Women's Center and the mentorship of Yale administrators like Lloyd Suttle and Martin Griffin. She also pays tribute to the collegiality and guidance of women such as Elga Wasserman, Etta Onat, Judith Brandenburg, Lorraine Siggins and Mary Arnstein. The extent to which issues of gender, as opposed to those of seniority, might be perceived as an exclusionary mechanism in the politics of Yale's administration is addressed. She recalls some of the major challenges in working with undergraduates, especially in respect of disciplinary issues relating to alcohol and sexual harassment. A lengthy consideration is offered of the work of Yale's Sexual Harassment Grievance Board, and her involvement in the creation of the Sexual Harassment and Assault Resource and Education Center [S.H.A.R.E.], concluding with an account of how the treatment of such matters has evolved at Yale.
  - Audiorecording, 8; ; 3 hours and 30 minutes
    - Use copy, 1
  - Edited transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1)
- Wasserman, Elga, 2007 May 24; Accession 2012-A-056